# EFFAT FARHANA

## effat.farhana@vanderbilt.edu

https://effat.github.io/

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Researcher with a focus on *Interpretable Machine Learning (ML)*, *Data Mining*, *Natural Language Processing (NLP)*, and *educational psychology*. Publications in EAAI@AAAI, GECCO, L@S, and EDM. Research focuses on the design, analysis, and implementation of data mining and machine learning systems addressing unique challenges arising in specific application domains, such as education and healthcare domains.

## **EDUCATION**

#### • Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) in Computer Science

Aug 2015 - April 2021

- Dissertation title: "Science Reading Behavior of Middle School Students within a Digital Literacy Platform"
- Adviser: Dr. Collin F. Lynch
- Committee: Dr. James Lester, Dr. Noboru Matsuda, and Dr. Teomara Rutherford
- North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC, USA

## • Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Science and Engineering

Feb 2011

- Graduated with Honours
- CGPA: 3.83/4.00, Rank:  $14_{th}$  in a class of 138
- Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

# AWARDS & HONORS

• Rising Star in Data Science- Jan 2021, University of Chicago.

For my Ph.D. work. organised by Center for Data and Computing (CDAC), University of Chicago. Link

• Travel award

To attend Women in Machine Learning (WiML) workshop, co-located with NeurIPS 2020 (virtual).

• Travel award

For CRA-WP Widening Participation Early and Mid Career Mentoring Workshop, 2020

- Scholarship by Women in Computer Science (WiCS), NC State To attend Grace Hopper Conference, 2018.
- Scholarship by ACM Richard Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing, 2020

  To present poster based on my Ph.D. work in ACM Student Research Competition.
- Dean's List Award

Received this award for achieving academic excellence for six semesters during the Bachelors program in Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology.

## SELECTED RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Vanderbilt University

Working in research projects involving people with autism spectrum disorder (ASD). Cross-disciplinary research between departments of computer science, psychology, and medical school at Vanderbilt.

• Topic: Visual Question Answering (VQA) on Social Reasoning (NLP, ML, Computer Vision)

- Developing a system to represent videos across modalities: audio, subtitles, and images to answer social reasoning questions e.g., "Is the boy upset?".
- Topic: Educational Game to Teach Social Skills to ASD Kids (ML, Data Mining, Psychology)
  - Designing user surveys and applying data mining and machine learning techniques to connect kids' in-game performance with social skills.

## North Carolina State University

- Topic: Interpretable ML Algorithm to Trace Students' Sequential Behaviors (Interpretable ML, NLP)
  - Designed a transformer-based model to predict 12,000 students' question scores incorporating contextual information of questions and learning activities. Proposed model performed better than state-of-the-art approaches.
  - Interpretable visualization of the transformer's attention can help teachers to identify students' study habits and performance (EAAI-AAAI 2022).
- Topic: Rule-based Algorithm for Interpretable Classification

(Interpretable ML)

- Developed a rule-based classification algorithm, BBO-RM, using an evolutionary algorithm, Biogeography- based optimization (BBO). BBO-RM performed significantly better compared to baseline classification algorithms on 14 UCI repository datasets (GECCO 2017).
- Implemented a parallel version of the BBO-RM algorithm utilizing Julia programming language's data slicing techniques and Julia's parallelization features. (GECCO 2018).
- Topic: Data-driven analysis to understand students' meta-cognitive reading behaviour (Data Mining)
  - Applied sequential pattern mining technique to understand reading and meta-cognitive behaviors patterns for 12.5K science and 16.2K social study student data. (L@S 2020).
- Topic: Empirical Software Engineering

(Qualitative Analysis)

- Derived bug categories in configuration management scripts (ICSE 2020).

#### **Publications**

## Peer-Reviewed Journals and Conference Publications

12. [EAAI@AAI 22] Predictive Student Modelling in an Online Reading Platform

Effat Farhana, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.

Twelfth AAAI Symposium on Educational Advances in Artificial Intelligence (EAAI-AAAI 2022) (In Press).

11. [L@S 20] Understanding Reading Behaviors of Middle School Students

Effat Farhana, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.

Proceedings of the Seventh ACM Conference on Learning @ Scale (L@S 2020).

10. **[ICLS 20]** Associations Between Self-Regulated Learning Strategies and Science Assignment Score in a Digital Literacy Platform

Effat Farhana, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.

Proceedings of the International Conference of the Learning Sciences (ICLS 2020).

9. [EDM 20] Investigating Relations between Self-Regulated Reading Behaviors and Science Question Difficulty

Effat Farhana, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.

Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Educational Data Mining (EDM 2020).

- 8. [ICSE 20] Gang of eight: A Defect Taxonomy for Infrastructure as Code Scripts Akond Rahman, Effat Farhana, Chris Parnin, and Laurie Williams.

  Proceedings of the 42nd International Conference on Software Engineering, (ICSE 2020)
- [EMSE 20] The 'as code' Activities: Development Anti-patterns for Infrastructure as Code Akond Rahman, Effat Farhana and Laurie Williams. Empirical Software Engineering. 25, 3430–3467 (EMSE 2020).

6. [ICSME 19] Synthesizing Program Execution Time Discrepancies in Julia Used for Scientific Software Effat Farhana, Nasif Imtiaz and Akond Rahman,

IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME 2019)

[MSR 19] Challenges with Responding to Static Analysis Tool Alerts
 Nasif Imtiaz, Akond Rahman, Effat Farhana and L. Williams.

 IEEE/ACM 16th International Conference on Mining Software Repositories (MSR 2019)

4. [GECCO 17] Biogeography-based Rule Mining for Classification Effat Farhana and Steffen Heber.

Proceedings of the Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference (GECCO 2017).

3. [Inf. Sci. 15] Constrained sequence analysis algorithms in computational biology Effat Farhana, and M. Sohel Rahman.

Information Sciences 295 (2015).

2. [Inf. Process. Lett. 12] Doubly-constrained LCS and hybrid-constrained LCS problems revisited Effat Farhana, and M. Sohel Rahman.

Information Processing Letters 112.13 (2012).

1. [SPIRE 15] Finite Automata Based Algorithms for the Generalized Constrained Longest Common Subsequence Problems

Effat Farhana, Jannatul Ferdous, Tanaeem M. Moosa, M. Sohel Rahman. 17th International Symposium of String Processing and Information Retrieval, (SPIRE 2010).

## Peer-Reviewed Workshop, Poster Publications, and Others

- [EDM 18] Predicting Post-College STEM Enrollment from Middle School Clickstream Data Effat Farhana, Maaz Saleem Kapadia, Wenjia Cao, and Collin F. Lynch. Workshop on Scientific Findings from the ASSISTments Longitudinal Data Competition: (EDM 2018).
- [GECCO 18] A Parallel Island Model for Biogeography-based Classification Rule Mining in Julia Samuel Ebert, Effat Farhana, and Steffen Heber.
   Proceedings of the Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference Companion (GECCO 2018).
- 3. [EDM 21] Feedback and Self-regulated Learning in Science Reading
  Effat Farhana, Andrew Potter, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.

  Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Educational Data Mining (EDM 2021) (Poster).
- [EDM 20] Self-Regulated Learning and Science Reading of Middle-School Students
   Effat Farhana, Teomara Rutherford, and Collin F. Lynch.
   Doctoral Consortium. The 13th International Conference on Educational Data Mining (EDM 2020).

### MENTORING

• Undergraduate Research Mentoring. North Carolina State University

Aug 2017- Aug 2018

 Co-advised Samuel Ebert on interpretable ML algorithm project. This work resulted in a student's lead author paper (GECCO 2018).

## SKILLS

Languages Java, Python, R, C, C++, Julia, Bash

Databases MySQL, Oracle, SQLAlchemy

Frameworks & Libraries Scikit-Learn, NLTK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch

# PROFESSIONAL SERVICE AND ORGANIZATIONAL EXPERIENCE

- Reviewer at Artificial Intelligence, Ethics, and Society (AIES) 2022
- Reviewer at Artificial Intelligence in Education (AIED) 2022
- Sub-reviewer at EDM 2021
- Shadow PC at Mining Software Repository (MSR), 2021 Conference
- Reviewer at ICLS 2020
- Judge for VandyHacks 2021 (Vanderbilt's premier student hackathon)
- Ph.D. panel member at Doctoral Recruiting Day 2020, NCSU
- Volunteered at NC State International Graduate Student Orientation 2017

# Professional Experience

• Postdoctoral Research Scholar Vanderbilt University

• Graduate Research Assistant (RA) North Carolina State University

• Graduate Teaching Assistant (TA) North Carolina State University

• Graduate Research Assistant (RA) North Carolina State University

• Lecturer, Computer Science
Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology

Jul 2021 - Present Nashville, TN

Aug 2020 - May 2021 Raleigh, NC

Aug 2016 - Aug 2020 Raleigh, NC

Aug 2015- Aug 2016 Raleigh, NC

Apr 2011 - Dec 2014 Dhaka, Bangladesh

Fall 2016 - Spring 2020

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## North Carolina State University

Teaching Assistant (TA)

- -TA for graduate level courses: Design and Analysis of Algorithm ( $\sim 200$  students), Database Management Concepts and Systems ( $\sim 150$  students), Software Engineering ( $\sim 30$  students), Artificial Intelligence ( $\sim 60$  students), and undergraduate level Data Structure and Algorithm ( $\sim 150$  students) course.
- Created assignments and exam questions, held office hours, and graded.

#### Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology

April 2011 - Dec 2014

- Lecturer in Computer Science and Engineering
  - Instructor for undergraduate level introductory programming language, design and analysis of algorithm, and compiler courses.

# INVITED TALKS

Machine Learning and Data Science for Social Good (Spring 2022)

Florida International University

Membership No.: 4570793

## Professional Memberships

- ACM Professional Member
- AAAI Member